Hello again. Welcome
to our fifth lecture on
respiratory physiology.
Today we're going to
look at lung mechanics,
and particularly at the
elastic properties of
the lungs themselves.
My name is Dr. Jörg Le Hest.
These are the session
objectives, which
are in line with the
event description.
This event focuses on
the forces involved in
normal breathing, with an
emphasis on compliance,
surface tension,
elasticity, and resistance.
The session also
explores additional
physiological as well as
pathological factors that
can alter these forces
and therefore airflow.
This slide shows the basic
biomechanics of breathing.
You can see that
during inhalation,
the muscles that are
used for breathing,
they contract, and as a result,
the ribcage expands and
air flows into the lungs.
This is an active
process and the muscles
that are used for it,
they must contract.
During quiet breathing,
exhalation is a passive
process which relies on the
relaxation of the muscles
that have been previously
used for inhalation
and the recoil that has
been stored in the system.
This image depicts the
largest muscle that we
use for breathing and
that is our diaphragm
which sits at the bottom
of our thoracic cavity.
This is an illustration
of the muscles
that we're using for breathing.
There's the principal
group and then there's the
accessory group. The principal
group for inspiration
involves the diaphragm
that we've already
looked at, which basically
increases the vertical
dimension of the thoracic
cavity by moving down.
And then we also have the
external intercostals,
the interchondral parts
of them, which are here,
that also contract
and as a result
lead to an elevation
of the ribs.
increasing the volume
of the ribcage.
Quiet breathing,
as we've already
discussed, is a
passive process.
And exploration
results from the recoil
of the system
returning to its normal
shape before the
breath was taken.
During active
breathing, we can use
additional muscles.
so here we have the
internal intercostals
which except for the
interchondral portions which
were used for inspiration
are used for forced
expiration also the abdominal
muscles ones that are
responsible for the six
pack the so-called six
pack are used for forced
expiration what's not shown
is the quadratus lumborum,
which leads to an additional
pull down of the ribs.
The accessory group is
up here and involves
the sternocleidomastoid
and the scalene group.
Again, muscle not shown is
the pectoralis minor, and
these muscles increase
the volume of the thoracic
chamber by basically lifting
the arms and this can be
seen in people that are
suffering from diseases that
belong to the COPD group
that these individuals tend
to expand the volume of their
thoracic cavity by lifting
their arms which makes
them look barrel-chested.
You have two pleural layers,
an outer one which is
the parietal pleura which
covers the entire interior
of the thoracic cavity and
the organs that are within
it and then we have an
inner pleura which is the
visceral pleura to which
our lungs are attached so
the lungs are not directly
attached to the thoracic
cavity but they're attached
to the parietal pleura,
which is attached to the
visceral pleura
via a fluid film.
That fluid and the space
in which it's located
is called the pleural
space, and we're going
to talk about that in
the next few minutes.
I would like to take a little
time and talk
about terminology.
So when we talk about
lung pressures, we
also refer it to
atmospheric pressure.
And when lung
pressure is equal to
atmospheric pressure,
it's designated zero.
Positive pressure, which
means an increase in
pressure, will then be a
number that's greater than
zero, one, two, three,
four, and so forth. Negative
pressure would be a pressure,
a collapsing pressure
that reduces the volume
of the lungs, and that
would be designated minus
1, 2, 3, 4, and so forth.
Another expression that we'll
use is transmural pressure.
When we talk of transmural
pressure, it's kind of
a vague description because
all it means is a comparison
of pressures inside a
compartment versus outside.
There are several ways
transmural pressure can be
defined, but basically
it describes in
pressure inside versus
pressure outside.
Another pressure that will
come across frequently
is the transpulmonary
pressure, And that is
defined as the pressure
difference between the
alveolar space, which is
inside the lungs, of course,
and the pleural cavity,
which is right here.
So you can see it right here,
the transpulmonary pressure.
Normal air pressure is
760 millimeters mercury.
And the pressure inside
the interpleural pressure
is only 756 millimeters
mercury. at rest, so there's
a pressure difference of
four millimeters mercury.
Here is a depiction of
the pleural space, which
exists between the visceral
pleural, that's this layer
here, and the parietal
pleural. The visceral pleural
demarcates the visceral
space in which we find
the alveoli, so that's the
inside of the lung here,
to the right, and the
parietal space is the space
between the parietal pleura
and the organs that it covers.
It's important to note
that the space, the
intrapleural space, sometimes
called pleural space,
but we call it intrapleural
space in most cases,
that that's filled with
a liquid and it contains
about 10 milliliters of
liquid as a total volume.
Now how does the liquid
get there? Well, there
are two pressures that
we need to consider. The
one is the hydrostatic
pressure, so that's the
pressure that the liquid
environment of the
surrounding spaces produce
and force upon the space.
And the other one is the
oncotic pressure, so that
is the pressure that exists
due to charged molecules
in the interstitium.
And you can see that the
hydrostatic pressure, the
pressure of liquid, is pointing
from both directions to
the interpleural space.
So liquid, the hydrostatic
pressure, is trying to
force liquid or water from
the varietal space and
from the visceral space
into the interpleural space.
Now the oncotic pressures
for both sides go the
opposite direction, and
overall they cancel each
other out. So your caudic
pressure is positive
5 centimeters water,
so now we switch we're
done with millimeters
mercury, and the hydrostatic
pressure is minus 5
centimeters water column.
What's important to notice,
or important to note,
is that the majority of
the fluid comes from the
parietal space. So which
makes sense because
there's not also all too
much fluid to be associated
with the interstitium
around the alveoli. So
most of it comes from
the other side and that
maintains the fluid level
in the intrapleural space.
So while there is constantly
fluid being released
into the interpleural space,
it's also always drained.
So there's a constant
fluid drainage through the
lymphatic system, and if
this malfunctions, then we
end up with too much fluid
in the interpleural space
and then in an end edema.
But on our normal conditions,
whatever is produced
doesn't stay around for
very long as it's being
drained via the lymphatics.
This image nicely
illustrates the relationship
between compliance
and elasticity, which
in physiology we
sometimes call elastance,
of objects, and it also
applies to the lungs.
so a an object that is
compliant is in terms of air
pressures is easy to expand
and a good example of that
is a shopping bag so it's
very easy to place things into
the bag not much force is
needed to expand the bag
now balloons on the other hand
they're somewhat compliant
because they can be expanded.
But as you all know,
the expansion, especially
of a small balloon,
can be very difficult
at the beginning.
So there's a lot of elasticity
and that elasticity,
especially at the
beginning of blowing up
a balloon, pushes back
and resists the force
of putting air into it.
So that is elasticity.
As the balloon then
expands, it gets easier
and easier to put air
into it, which means
that the compliance at
this point increases.
This image shows an
experiment where a lung was
excised and placed into
a salient-filled jar,
and then the system is
hooked up to a vacuum pump.
So applying a vacuum means
applying negative pressure,
suction in other words,
and that's what's being
done here. as vacuum is applied
to the lung it increases
its volume and inspiration
occurs until the
maximal point up here upon
which the vacuum is is released
and then expiration occurs
and due to the natural
recoil or elasticity of
the lung, the lung returns
to its original size at
the bottom of the line. So
this behavior here is called
a pressure-volume loop.
And what's noteworthy about
this is that the forces
that are needed to inspire
the lung or to increase
its volume are different
than the forces that it
takes to reduce the volume
of the lung and to expire.
And that relationship where
these forces differ between
inspiration and expiration
is called hysteresis.
So the question then arises,
so this has to do with
compliance, and the question
arises why the compliance
of inspiration is smaller
than the compliance of
expiration. I'll give you a
second to think about this.
well it has to do with
the water molecules that
are inside the alveoli
and the difficulty to
expand these alveoli
initially so that's where much
of the collapsing forces
of the lungs come from
is from the surface
tension that these water
molecules produce and so
one has to get initially
over a threshold
and then it becomes
easier to increase the volume.
So you can see that the
example of a balloon and its
elasticity is actually a very
good one. The same happens
with our lungs, but for
different reasons, of course,
because there is no liquid
film inside a balloon.
But initially, the balloon,
as it's small, it's very
difficult to inflate. And
then as it gets bigger, it
becomes easier. So the
same is true for our lungs.
But the reason behind
it is that it's the
surface tension of
water because all the
alveoli are aligned
with a water film.
And these water molecules
attract each other.
and so this attractive
force leads to reduced
compliance especially at
low lung volumes in the
following we will be looking
at the lungs and the chest
wall and it's a very this
is a very good depiction
so I just wanted to show
you this so you get used
to the kind of depiction
these are the conducting
airways that lead to
the alveoli. So this one
alveolus represents all of
the alveoli in our lung.
This round triangle
represents the chest wall.
Here we have the
visceral pleura, here we
have the parietal
pleural layer, and in
between them we have
the interpleural space.
So the only thing in
this depiction that's
Somewhat off in
terms of the reality
is the size of the
interplural space.
Of course, the size in the
natural interplural space
is much smaller and the
size here is exaggerated.
So inside the interplural
space, and this on the left
is the normal situation, we
have a negative pressure.
Negative pressure is the
same as vacuum. I could
say vacuum. There's a
vacuum that exists there.
The question becomes, how
does the vacuum get there?
Well, there are several
factors, but the main factors
are that the surface tension
of the alveoli pull on
the visceral pleura in the
direction of the arrow.
The chest wall here
on the other side
has a spring-like
characteristic and wants to
slightly expand. So you can
see what it wants to expand
to here in the dotted
line on the other side.
So that pulls on the parietal
pleura in exactly
the opposite way.
So we have the alveoli
pulling at the interpleural
space in one direction,
and we have the chest wall
and the parietal pleura
pulling at the interpleural
space the other way, and
then the result is a vacuum.
And this is the negative
pressure, and now we'll
turn to pressures in
centimeters of water. So all
of the pressures that you
see from here on forward
are in centimeters of water and
not anymore in
millimeters mercury.
So what happens
when we puncture
the parietal pleura
for instance?
Well that is
something that happens
and it's called pneumothorax.
That's common in car
accidents when people are not
strapped or not strapped
into their seat with the
seat belt and they slam
into the steering wheel with
a ribcage then it frequently
happens that one of the
ribs break and then it
punctures the parietal pleura
and so then what happens
is that the vacuum or the
negative pressure that
existed here it disappears
so it becomes zero and what
happens then is that the
chest wall expands as it
naturally would because
there's nothing holding it
back and the forces that
exist inside the alveoli
they will have the alveoli
collapse and that situation
is then the pneumothorax
let's now look at the
compliance of the lungs chest
wall system here on the
left we have indicated
expanding forces on the right
collapsing forces on the
top we have lung volumes
that are above the functional
residual capacity remember
that the frc the the
end of the frc is at the
end of tidal volume so when
you breathe out that's
exactly indicated by this
line and then we have three
things we're looking at.
We're looking at the forces
that affect the chest
wall, or that the chest
wall exerts, I should say,
the forces that the
lung tissue exerts,
and then in purple,
we have them combined.
So here at the functional
visceral capacity at FRC,
we can see that the chest
wall is trying to expand
so the rib cage is arranged
in a way that when we
breathe out it wants to
expand and you can test that
with yourself just breathe
out and then naturally see
what your chest wall
wants to do so up to
this point here when
we start breathing in
there's a negative or
there's an expanding force
and that ends with the
chest wall at this point
Now, with the lungs,
we have the situation
where the lungs always
want to collapse,
always. There's not one
point where the lungs
want to expand the
lung's chest wall system.
And you probably guessed
it, why that is the
case. Well, that is
the force inside all
of the alveoli, the
collapsing force, which
is exerted by the
surface tension of water.
So even at lung
volumes lower than
FRC, the lung still
wants to collapse.
And so when we put these
forces both together,
you can see that
starting with inspiration
and the beginning
of a tidal breath,
both systems if they are
overlaid are in the collapsing
mode and the only way to
overcome this is by using
our inspiratory muscles
so that is why inspiration
must be an active process
so this is at the end of
inspiration and by that time
both systems, chest wall and
lungs, want to collapse
the lung chest wall system.
So and then when we start
contracting our inspiratory
muscles that's exactly
what happens. The
recoil then leads to the
collapse of the system and
that can be passive. So
this explains once again,
why inspiration is active and
why expiration can be passive.
Now we're exploring diseases
affecting lung compliance.
Now there are rarely
diseases that affect
chest wall compliance,
so in most cases that
remains normal, which
is indicated here.
But there are diseases
that affect lung
compliance. And we
have two examples,
one is emphysema
and one is fibrosis.
So what we have in
emphysema is a partial
destruction of elastic
properties of the lungs.
So the lungs of
emphysema patients become
more compliant, so
it gets easier to put
air into those and
one needs less force
with exerted by inspiratory
muscles to breathe in.
And you can see this here,
that the curve of airway
pressures is on the
collapsing side with emphysema
patients, but it's much closer
to the expanding foresight
than in normal patients or
than in normal individuals.
So in other words, it's
very, very easy for
emphysema patients to
expand their lungs,
which on the contrary means
that it's becoming more
difficult for them to
breathe out and empty their
lungs of the air that
they just breathed in. so
the lungs of emphysema
patients is too compliant
and not enough elastic now
the opposite is true with
individuals that suffer
from patients that suffer
from fibrosis so in In
this case, there are
additional fibers inserted
into the lung tissue and they
make the lungs less
compliant and more elastic.
So it becomes harder
to expand the lungs.
but then it's fairly
easy to breathe out and
have the lungs collapse
but individuals with
suffering from fibrosis
typically are not able to
expand the lungs to their
full intended volume
so in the end that means
that in individuals
with emphysema the
functional residual capacity
is higher than in normal
individuals you can
see this here this blue
dot purple is normal
and in individuals with
fibrosis the functional
residual capacity is
lower than in normals
so in other words
emphysema patients have
a very easy time to
expand their lungs
and a hard time to
contract their lungs and
fibrosis patients are
suffering from the opposite
which is they're having
a hard time expanding
their lungs due to
increased elasticity,
but have an easier time
to collapse their lungs.
We already explored
the surface tension of
alveoli, so this should
be a brief review.
You know that this is guided
by the law of Laplace,
which applies to small
spheres, And you know
that P, the collapsing
pressure, is equal to two
times the surface tension
divided by the radius.
So the collapsing pressure,
if you compare two spheres,
a large alveolus and a
small alveolus, then the
radius component is larger
in the larger alveolus, which
proportionally reduces the
surface tension component,
making these collapsing
forces smaller compared to
the collapsing forces of a
smaller alveolus. On a smaller
VLi, this radius portion
of the equation is smaller,
which makes the surface
tension portion more
dominant, meaning that smaller
VLi tend more to collapse
than larger VLi. You
already know that our system
counteracts this because if
there was no such mechanism
then all of the smaller VLI
would collapse and all of
the air that was in there
would be transferred to the
larger VLI and then the
larger VLI would collapse
and put their air into even
larger VLI so So that's,
of course, not consistent
with respiratory function,
and death would ensue. And
for this reason, we have
surfactant, which we already
looked at, which increases
lung compliance and prevents
atelectasis and ensures
the uniformity of function
of small and larger VLI.
Neonatal respiratory
distress syndrome is a
situation in which mostly
premature babies are
born without sufficient
amounts of surfactant. And
you can see this here
in this x-ray that the
right lung is perfectly
fine. So apparently
there's enough surfactant
inside the right lung,
but the left lung is
collapsed. So it's
completely opaque,
which means that all of
the alveoli in the left
lung are collapsed.
As a guideline,
babies that are born
before gestational week 24,
they never have surfactant and
always require intervention.
And babies that are
born during gestational
weeks 24 to 35, the
process is uncertain.
So this is what normal
alveoli look like with
surfactant, and that's
what alveoli look like with
insufficient amounts of
surfactant and after collapse.
So what can you do?
So when you know that a baby is
born before its
actual due time,
one treatment that
is frequently or
that is the standard
of treatment is
injections of the
mother with steroids.
So steroids aid
lung maturation and
with that also
surfactant production.
If this doesn't happen,
then in most cases
treatment consists of
nasal continuous positive
airway pressure or NCPAP
and doesn't require surgery.
So positive pressure
needs to be applied
to keep the baby's
alveoli open and there
are machines that can
do that. And in most
cases, that is the
solution to the problem.
let's briefly explore airflow
pressure and resistance
relationships just to
see what the dominant
forces are and airflow is
described as delta p which
is the pressure gradient
that exists between the
beginning of a tube or a
system and the end of it
divided by airway resistance
which is R, and resistance
then further can be
described as Poirier's law.
So where resistance is
equal to A times, that's
the letter eta, the
Greek letter eta, smaller
case viscosity of inspired
air, times the length
of the system, divided
by pi, Pi because airways
are circular, more or
less, times the radius
to the fourth exponent,
or to the fourth power.
But right away, looking
at Prasur's law, you
can see that the radius
is the dominant force in
this equation. And that
if anyone wanted to
make changes to the
conductance of an airway
system, that manipulating
its radius is the best
way to do it because it
has such a high weight.
Let's now look over
here. So here we have
resistance of the
airway system plotted
against some of the
components of the system.
And you can see that airway
resistance is pretty high
in the trachea is the
highest at the level of the
bronchus the two main
bronchi and then the smaller
bronchi still remains
higher until we get down to
the bronchioles and then it
gets very low so initially
that's a puzzling thing
to look at but if you
consider that we are turning
from a system of a sequential
flow here to a system
with parallel flow where
the air has a million
choices in terms of the route
that it goes, that then
can explain why the overall
resistance goes down.
That's due to parallel flow.
This illustration shows how
changes in airway resistance
through airway dynamiter
are being accomplished.
So on the left side we have
a normal airway dynamiter
and a normal lung and on
the right side we have
an inflamed lung and
reduced diameter airways. In
this particular case, this
is likely due to the activity
of pro-inflammatory
mediators such as histamine
and leukotrients and they
just cause constriction.
Normally, without infection
and without inflammation,
the autonomic nervous system
is responsible, and you
already know that the
sympathetic branch leads to
relaxation and airway dilation,
as in this case, and that
this works through adrenergic
beta receptors and can
be accomplished via adrenergic
beta-receptor agonists.
The one natural
agonist that comes from
our adrenal medulla
is epinephrine,
and there are drugs
that accomplish the
same. In case this
down here happens,
isoproteranol and albuterol
can be administered.
Then the parasympathetic
branch does the opposite.
It leads to airway
constriction, similar to what
you see here, and it
works through muscarinic
agonists, which can be
either muscarine or carbosol.
Carbosol is also used
as an ophthalmic agent,
and there it is used
to decrease intraocular
pressure after
cataract surgery so but
in airways it causes
airway constriction
um these activities can
be blocked with muscarinic
antagonists and one of those
is atropine but Atropine
also has a downside because
it negatively impacts
cardiac function, so one
has to be careful with this.
Now that we know how
important the control of
resistance is in airway
function, let's look at some
other factors that can
change airway resistance.
One we've already looked
at previously, and that had
to do with the interdependence
of alveoli. So, when one
alveolus is pulled open,
that has an effect on nearby
alveoli, which are then
indirectly also pulled open.
The same is true with
the opposite. So, if one
alveolus, let's say this one
here in the center, collapses
or closes up due to a
condition such as asthma,
then the other alveoli nearby
will do the same thing.
And that then, because it
affects a larger system,
that can change airway
resistance quite dramatically.
Another thing that matters is
the viscosity of inspired air.
Here, again, our viscosity,
Greek letter eta.
And it's important to
note that air viscosity,
as we've seen also
being a factor in
Perseu's law, can change
with air temperature.
And generally, colder air is
easier to breathe
than warmer air.
This also bears significance
for deep-sea divers,
and they are putting
helium into their air
mixture up to 3% typically,
and that's because
helium is much less viscous
than the regular air
that we breathe, so it
makes it easier under
those deep-sea pressure
conditions to breathe.
Another mechanism
that we briefly looked
at is compensatory
bronchoconstriction.
So here on the example you
can see that if we encounter
a situation where one
bronchus is poorly ventilated
then the system recognizes
this and it then
regulates so that blood flow
to this poorly ventilated
bronchus is completely
shut off and instead it
increases alternative pathways
and increases blood flow
to the bronchi that are
very well when ventilated
so it compensates depending
on where poorly ventilated
bronchi are located and
this process is called
compensatory bronchonstriction
if you look at this
poorly ventilated alveolus
then you can appreciate
that the alveolar air so the
partial pressure of oxygen
inside this alveolus and
the partial pressure of
carbon dioxide is
pretty much the same as
that of the ambient
outside air because there's
little to no exchange
that occurs there so
that then leads to a
decrease in the partial
pressure of CO2 in the
surrounding tissues,
that, due to the
bicarbonate buffer
system, increases the
pH, and an increased
pH is a signal for
bronchoconstriction.
So that is how this
regulation happens,
due to a drop in
partial pressure of CO2,
which then leads to
an increase in pH, and
that then leading to
bronchoconstriction.
Here we're looking at
the breathing cycle, and
the breathing cycle is
divided into three phases,
A, B, and D, actually,
where A is the resting
phase in between two
breaths, B is
inspiration, and D is
expiration. C just
designates the maximum point
of inspiration and
beginning of expiration.
So as we breathe
in, the intrapleural
pressure goes
down. So remember,
as we expand our
ribcage and breathe in,
at the same time we're
pulling the alveoli open,
and so the alveoli
as they open produce
an inward force they're
trying to collapse
and the chest wall is
trying to expand and
that pulls the interpleural
space from both
sides and that increases
the interpleural pressure
from minus five to
maximally minus eight
and the units here
are centimeters
water not millimeters
mercury anymore
As we breathe out,
the opposite happens, and the
now more negative pressure
returns to a less negative
pressure as we expire.
But the intraplural
pressure, and
that's the key,
always stays negative.
Otherwise, the lungs
would collapse.
At the same time,
when we breathe in,
the alveolar
pressure goes down.
and as a result, air
flows into the lungs.
As we breathe out,
we reduce the
volume of the lungs,
alveolar pressure
goes up, forcing the
air out of the
lungs, and we expire.
So this is the breathing cycle
depicted in a different way.
And one thing to keep your
eyes on is the transmural
pressure. So that's the
yellow arrow, and it's
calculated as the alveolar
pressure inside the
alveoli minus the interpleural
pressure. So that's
the interpleural cavity,
and let's minus that.
And let's follow the
breathing cycle. So here we
are at rest, and at rest
the alveolar pressure is 0,
and the intrapleural
pressure is minus 5, 0
minus minus 5, remember
we need to deduct,
mean it's the same as 0 plus
5, so minus minus is plus,
so 0 plus 5 means that the
transmural pressure is 5.
Now as we breathe in
the chest wall expands
and the interpleural
pressure as a result
increases and the
alveolar pressure
drops down so that
air can flow in.
So the transmural pressure
here is minus 1 minus minus
6.5, which is minus 1 plus
6.5, which is plus 5.5. And
at maximal inspiration,
the intra-alveolar pressure
again is zero. At this point,
the lungs or chest wall,
lungs and chest wall are
at their maximal expansion.
So there's a huge pull at
the interpleural space.
Therefore,
the negative pressure is
minus 8 at this point.
If we do the calculation
of the transmural
pressure, we have 0
minus minus 8, which is
0 plus 8, being plus
8. And then we return
to the starting point,
start to breathe out.
At that point, when
we're breathing out,
the lungs are reducing their
volume. That produces a
positive pressure inside. It's
typically toggling between
plus one and minus one,
inspiration and expiration.
At that point, there's
less negative pressure
inside the interpleural
space. Let's do the math.
Plus 1 minus minus 6 is plus
1 plus 6, I'm sorry, plus
1 minus minus 6.5, which
is the same as plus 1 plus
6.5, which is plus 7.5, and
then we return to normal.
My point is that at all
stages, the transmural
pressure is positive
and is pointing outward.
so on by pointing outward
and being positive the
transmural pressure is what
prevents the collapse of
the lungs so in other
words in order to prevent
lung collapse transmural
pressure always has to be
positive that's the takeaway
message from the slide
So here we have a situation
of forced expiration.
It's a little bit different
than tidal breathing.
And the big question
here is, will the lungs
collapse with positive
interpleural pressure?
So because in both cases,
in a normal individual
and also in an
individual suffering from
emphysema, we have positive
interpleural pressure.
I'm sorry, that's the
interpleural pressure here.
The answer to the
question is obvious.
If the answer was yes,
then anybody playing a wind
instrument would collapse
their lungs. So it cannot
be true that forced expiration
leads to lung collapse.
At least it doesn't under
normal circumstances.
So somebody playing the
trumpet can do so, and it's
actually a good exercise.
It's a healthy exercise,
and it will not collapse
somebody's lung. So it's
possible to have a positive
intraplural pressure.
What's important, however
is that the transmural
pressure has to stay
positive so the pressure
difference between in and
out has to stay positive
that's what the transmural
pressure is so let's
do this for a normal
individual without health
conditions so here in
the airways at forced
expiration remember this
is forced expiration, we
have a positive pressure
of 25 centimeters water,
and
that's at this
point plus 25 minus
plus 20, which is
minus 20, we end up
with a transmural
pressure of plus 5.
At the bottom of the
alveoli, we have an alveolar
pressure of plus 35 minus
plus 20, which is minus
20, we end up with a
transmural pressure of 15.
So we already know from
the previous slide that
as long as the transmural
pressure is positive,
lungs don't collapse.
Now if we do this with an
individual or for an individual
suffering from emphysema,
the situation is similar
but not the same. So you can
see that the intrapleural
pressure is the same
but the pressures inside
the alveoli have changed and
inside the airways so and
that's because of the
diminished elastic recoil in
emphysema so emphysema leads
to or involves inflammation
and that inflammation
destroys a lot of the elastic
fibers that are able to
do the recoil in lungs. So
remember for emphysema, in
individuals with emphysema,
it's easy to expand their
lungs because their lungs
have increased compliance.
But at the same time,
it's more difficult for
them to force the air out of
their lungs because they
have reduced elastic recoil.
So in this example here, in the
large airways leading
to the alveoli,
an individual with emphysema
only has airway pressure
as a part of forced
expiration of plus 15, because
they cannot be aided much
by the elastic recoil,
so they can force all they
want, but there's less
elastic recoil which can
provide additional force to
produce more airway pressure.
At the same time, the
interpleural pressure
has not changed. So let's
do the math. We have plus
15 minus plus 20, which is
minus 20. So at this
point, we have a transmural
pressure that is minus 5
and actually points towards
collapse. So this large
airway would be collapsed.
Now in the alveoli, the
positive pressure is plus 25.
Minus plus 20, which is
minus 20, is still plus 5.
So here at the site of
the alveoli, there's still
positive transmural
pressure, which prevents
collapse, but there's reduced
or no airflow due to at
least the partial collapse
of the large airways.
In order to overcome this,
individuals with suffering
from emphysema they
breathe with pursed lips
so they produce additional
pressure that way when
breathing out and they
breathe more slowly and that
increases this number
here slightly and prevents
the collapse due to
negative transmural pressure
let's do one more question
this one is on the more
challenging side a 64 year
old retired sandblaster
presents with progressive
shortness of breath
and a dry hacking cough
a high resolution ct
scan of the chest reveals
diffuse interstitial
thickening and scarring
consistent with idiopathic
pulmonary fibrosis how
does this condition alter
the physical forces of
the respiratory system and
what is its effect on the
pressure volume loop a
it increases lung
compliance shifting the
pressure volume loop
upward and to the left
well this is incorrect
because diseases a disease
that increases lung
compliance is emphysema
so here we're dealing
with the enzymatic
destruction of elastin
and that results in
the lung becoming more
compliant and easier to inflate
so patients with emphysema
don't have a problem
inflating their lungs but
they're having problems
deflating their lungs in
other words getting air out.
B, it decreases
the inward elastic
recoil of the lungs,
shifting the resting
functional residual
capacity upward.
So in respiratory diseases
we actually have an increase
of the inward elastic
recoil, not a decrease so
because of the lay down of
collagen fibers the lung gets
harder to inflate and so
there's more of an inward
pull in the parenchyma and
that actually shifts the
resting functional residual
capacity downward so the
lungs become smaller in the
resting state shifting the
FRC downward so that's
why B is incorrect. D, it
eliminates the outward chest
wall recoil, forcing the
chest wall to collapse inward
during quiet respiration.
So this disease, pulmonary
fibrosis, is a parenchymal
disease. Parenchymal means
of the inside tissue, and
it has nothing to do with
the outside chest wall.
so the chest wall itself
stays unaffected and you know
operates as it normally
would and that's why d is
incorrect e it decreases
airway resistance making the
patient's forced expiratory
volume in one second
abnormally high so we haven't
really particularly talked
about fev1 but it's a measure
that's used clinically
looking at the air expired
in one second and there's
two things wrong with
this so the one is that it
decreases airway resistance
so this is not an obstructive
disease that we're
dealing with here and then
secondly because of the air
the lungs being fibrotic and
much smaller to begin with
also the air that's expired
in the initial for a second
is abnormally low and
not high so that leaves us
with c as the appropriate
and correct answer choice
it decreases lung compliance
that's true decrease of
lung compliance means it
gets harder to inflate
requiring a much larger
negative intrapleural space
to achieve a normal tidal
volume if you remember
the intrapleural space is
always negative and make
sure that the lungs don't
collapse and the fact that
one has to expend much more
force to inflate a fibrotic
lung the it takes much
longer and it requires much
more effort to pull the
lungs open and that makes
the intra pleural space
much more negative and
pressure than in a healthy
lung right I hope that all
makes sense and thank you
As always, resources
can be found on
the CPG that accompanies
this lecture.
If you would be so kind,
please give me some feedback.
Let me know what worked,
what needs work, and
thanks for listening. Bye.